Alvah Posen Papers
Alvah Posen Papers
1919-1959
Posen, Alvah.
3.5 linear ft.
Papers of the American comic strip cartoonist. Original artwork for product advertising for Pepsi-Cola and Wheaties, comic strips (proof sheets and clippings), correspondence, his idea file for comic strips (1922-1951), memorabilia and photographs. Correspondents include Milton Caniff, Al Capp, Dwight D. Eisenhower, Rube Goldberg, Vernon Greene, Fred Harman, W. Averell Harriman, National Cartoonists Society, Franklin D. Roosevelt, Jr., Charles M. Schulz, and Fred Waring.
149528
Biographical History
Alvah "Al" Posen (1895-1960) was an American cartoonist best known for his long-running strip Sweeney and Son.
Born in New York City, Posen served in the Army during World War I and then traveled in the Orient as a member of a geological and mining expedition. Although he had no formal training in art, Posen sold his first comic strip, Them Days Is Gone Forever (later renamed Them Days Are Gone Forever, to United Features Syndicate in 1921. The strip featured a short tune accompanied by a limerick-style rhyme. Within a year the strip was running daily in one hundred newspapers. Posen discontinued it in 1927.
His second comic strip, Ella and Her Fella, while employing the same limerick format, ran only a short time. In 1933 Posen began Sweeney and Son for the Chicago Tribune - New York News syndicate, which ran for 25 years; for many of those years it ran in conjunction with a four-panel four-word rhyming gag strip called Jinglet, also by Posen. In 1949 he revived the scheme of Them Days Is Gone Forever and renamed it Rhymin' Time. While engaging in political and social satire in his comic art, Posen was most interested in portraying the humanly amusing side of life.
Al Posen was a co-producer of the first Marx Brothers motion picture, a silent short which was a financial flop. As a member of the National Cartoonists Society, he originated the idea of cartoonists' shows for American servicemen overseas. Posen died June 10, 1960.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Alvah Posen Papers consists of artwork, comic strips, correspondence, ideas for comics, memorabilia and photographs.
Correspondence consists of letters from newspaper and advertising clients, the Treasury Department, admirers requesting original drawings, and fellow cartoonists, among them Rube Goldberg, Al Capp, and Milton Caniff. A large part of the miscellaneous correspondence from 1955-1959 concerns Posen's role as Director of Overseas Shows for the National Cartoonists Society. Also included are a number of carbons of Posen's replies to letters received. A letter of 7 Jul 1948 from Posen to Richard Clarke of the Chicago Tribune gives a history of Them Days Is Gone Forever.
Ideas for comics consists mostly of letters received from fans, with suggestions and ideas for Jinglet and Them Days Is Gone Forever.
Memorabilia includes a report and test of a commercial strip for Wheaties cereal and National Cartoonists Society materials.
Original artwork contains pieces by Posen. There are sketches for commercial art pieces (some of which incorporate his strips, such as a rough for Them Days Is Gone Forever incorporating an ad for Ingram's Shaving Cream) and miscellaneous other pieces, such as an original colored strip of "The Roundies and the Squares."
Photographs contains portraits of Posen, portraits of others inscribed to Posen and images of cartoonist related events.
Printed material consists of proofs and newspaper clippings of Jinglet, Rhymin' Time, Sweeney and Son, Them Days Is Gone Forever. Some of these were originally pasted into scrapbooks which have been disassembled. In some cases two different strips were printed on the same sheet or pasted on the same page in a scrapbook, so there is some overlap of titles and dates in this section.
Arrangement of the Collection
Artwork is subdivided into commercial and non-commercial. Comic strips are arranged alphabetically by title and within that chronologically. Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent; miscellaneous items at the end are arranged chronologically. Ideas for comics are arranged alphabetically by title. Memorabilia is arranged alphabetically by type or topic.
Related Material
A eulogy for Al Posen and correspondence with Posen are located in the
Vernon Greene Papers
.
has more than 150 collections of cartoonist's papers. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Cartoonists; Caniff, Milton Arthur, 1907-1988 -- Correspondence.; Capp, Al, 1909-1979 -- Correspondence.; Goldberg, Rube, 1883-1970 -- Correspondence.; Greene, Vernon Van Atta -- Correspondence.; Posen, Alvah -- Archives.; Pepsi-Cola Company.; Advertising -- Food.; Sweeney and son.; Them days are gone forever.; Rhymin time.; Jinglet.; Schulz, Charles M. (Charles Monroe), 1922-2000 -- Correspondence.; Waring, Fred, 1900-1984 -- Correspondence.; National Cartoonists Society.; American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Comic books, strips, etc.; Advertising -- Soft drinks.; Awards.; Cartoons (humorous images); Clippings (information artifacts); Comics.; Correspondence.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Proofs (printed matter); Commercial art.; Cartoonists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mrs. Barbara Greene; transferred from the Vernon Greene Papers, 1972, 2010; transferred from the C.D. Russell Cartoons, 1967, 2011.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Amarillo Globe, 1949; about a Jinglet contest (Box 1)
  - American Theatre Wing, 1946-1948 (Box 1)
  - Caniff, Milt, 1946; 1949,; 1956-1958 (Box 1)
  - Capp, Al, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Coogan, Jackie, 1923; letter on Coogan's behalf asking for an original cartoon (Box 1)
  - Eisenhower, Dwight D., 1955 (Box 1)
  - Family, 1919-1920; undated; to and from Posen's mother and sister (Box 1)
  - Fisher, Bud, 1944; undated; includes three Mutt and Jeff Christmas cards (Box 1)
  - Goldberg, Rube, 1946; 1956-1957,; undated (Box 1)
  - Greene, Vern, undated (Box 1)
  - Harman, Fred, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Harriman, Averell, 1959 (Box 1)
  - Knox Reeves Advertising, 1944-1947; 1950; mostly concerning the Wheaties campaign (Box 1)
  - McCoy, Wilson, 1957-1958 (Box 1)
  - National Cartoonists Society, 1951; 1957-1958,; undated (Box 1)
  - Polumbaum, Ted and Nyna, undated (Box 1)
  - Roosevelt, Franklin D., 1949 (Box 1)
  - Schulz, Charles, 1956 (Box 1)
  - Thompson Koch Advertising Company, mostly Bristol Myers, regarding Ingram shaving cream and other ads (Box 1)
  - La Roe, Cap, See Thompson Koch Advertising Company.
  - Hopkins, Howard, See Thompson Koch Advertising Company.
  - Cox, Blake, See Knox Reeves Advertising.
  - Trachet, Don, 1958; undated (Box 1)
  - United Feature Syndicate, 1922; includes letter regarding the Kansas City Star's first-ever purchase of a comic strip for its paper: Them Days (Box 1)
  - United States Treasury, 1942; 1949-1951,; 1955,; 1957,; undated; most relating to Posen's work on Savings Bond campaigns; includes photos (Box 1)
  - Walsh, J. Martyn, regarding illustrations for Walsh's book; 1952 (Box 1)
  - Waring, Fred, 1948-1949; includes photos (Box 1)
  - Zaroubin, Georgi N., 1958; Soviet ambassador (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous
    - 1921-1946, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1958-1959, undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
- Ideas for comics
  - "Jinglet", 1926-1935 (Box 2)
  - "Mr. Bingo", 1925 (Box 2)
  - "Mr. Garz, the Man from Mars" (missing as of 12/17/09)
  - "Rhymes of Second Childhood" (Box 2)
  - "Rhymin' Time", 1922-1951; 3 folders (Box 2)
- Memorabilia
  - Awards, 1942-1958 (Box 2)
  - Biographical material, 1949; printed material (Box 2)
  - Clippings, 1922-1951 (Box 2)
  - Comic strip promotional materials, 1942-1949 (Box 2)
  - Development and test of advertising strip, 1945 (Box 2)
  - National Cartoonists Society, 1948-1954; printed material, savings bonds; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Photographs (Box 2)
  - Programs and invitations, 1927-1959 (Box 2)
- Original artwork
  - A Word About Colgate, undated (Box 3)
  - A Word About Ex-Lax, undated (Box 3)
  - A Word About Ingram's and Vitalis, undated (Box 3)
  - A Word About Lifebuoy, undated (Box 3)
  - A Word About Old Gold Cigarettes, undated (Box 3)
  - A Word About Palmolive, undated (Box 3)
  - A Word About... (miscellaneous), undated (Box 3)
  - Beech Nut Gum, undated (Box 3)
  - Chickie & Choosie / Ingram's Shaving Cream, undated (Oversize 3)
  - El Producto (cigars?) (missing as of 12/17/09), undated (Box 1)
  - Good Old Ben Bromo Selzer, undated (Oversize 3)
  - It's Wheaties Every Morning, undated (Box 3)
  - Lifebuoy, undated (Box 3)
  - Mr. Garz the Man from Mars, undated (Oversize 3)
  - Nature's Awakening, undated (Oversize 3)
  - Pepsi Cola, undated (Oversize 3)
  - Wheaties, undated (Oversize 3)
  - Works by others, 1956; undated; Charles Payne and drawing of Posen by unidentified (Oversize 3)
  - Wrigley's, undated (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, undated; Jinglet, Them Days, Sweeney & Son Christmas card (missing as of 12/17/09) (Box 1)
- Photographs
  - Bond Tour- Des Moines, Iowa, 1949 (Box 3)
  - Detroit Christmas party, 1946 (Box 3)
  - Library of Congress, Oct 1949 (Box 3)
  - Metropolitan Group- the National Newspaper Network, 1952 (Box 3)
  - Metro Sunday Comics party, circa 1952 (Box 3)
  - Portraits, undated (Box 3)
  - Police headquarters lineup; Wilkenson, Albert, 1949; 1951 (Box 3)
  - Tennis, undated (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, undated; some portraits inscribed to Posen (Box 3)
- Printed material
  - Call for Mr. Bingo, undated; proofs (Oversize 3)
  - Ella and Her Fella / Jinglet, 1931-1932; color tearsheets (Oversize 3)
  - Jinglet, 1935; clippings (Box 1)
  - Pepsi Cola, undated (Oversize 3)
  - Promotional material, 1920s; undated (Map-case 1, Drawer 107)
  - Rhymin' Time, 1950; clippings (Box 1)
  - Rhymin' Time, 1949-1950; daily proof sheets (Oversize 3)
  - Rhymin' Time, 1949-1950; proof sheets (Oversize 1)
  - Sweeney & Son, 1943-1944; color proofs tearsheets (Oversize 3)
  - Sweeney & Son, 1935; clippings (Box 1)
  - Sweeney & Son, 1941-1943; 1946-1948; clippings; 2 scrapbooks (Oversize 4)
  - Sweeney & Son, oversize, 1934-1955; 1958-1959; clippings; (missing as of 12/17/09); 2 folders
  - Sweeney & Son / Jinglet, 1936-1941; 1948-1949; proof sheets; 7 folders (Oversize 2)
  - Them Days Are Gone Forever, 1921-1925; 1944; proof sheets (Box 1)
  - Them Days Are Gone Forever / Jinglet, 1935; clippings (Box 1)
  - Thompson's Malted Milk, undated; proofs (Box 3)
  - Wheaties, undated; proofs (Box 3)
  - Willie Mite comic strip, 1945; 1948-1949; proofs (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, undated; negative proofs (Box 3)